# MATAN SHTEPEL

 $(925) \cdot 922 \cdot 9254 \diamond \text{matan.shtepel@gmail.com} \diamond \text{matanshtepel.com}$ 

Last updated: Dec. 2022.  $\diamond$  Most recent version: here

### **OVERVIEW**

So far, my research has been in cryptography, with an emphasis on secure multiparty computation (MPC) and oblivious random access memory (ORAM). I am currently in the process of applying to P.h.D programs in theoretical computer science.

#### **EDUCATION**

# University of California, Los Angeles

Sep. 2021 - March 2023 (expected)

B.S.E Computer Science with concentration in Pure Math.

GPA: 3.90/4.00 (Ongoing, Fall 2022 factored in)

Research in cryptography

Primary advisor: Prof. Rafail Ostrovsky (UCLA) Secondary advisor: Prof. Brett Falk (Upenn)

Organized the UCLA Theoretical Computer Science Guild Organized UCLA Engineering Transfer Center research events

# Las Positas Community College

June 2020 - May 2021

A.S Computer Science

A.S Math. GPA: 3.95/4.00

Honors project advised by Dr. William Pezzaglia: Quaternion-based Graphics

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

In alphabetical order unless stated otherwise.

• Mark Burgin, Matan Shtepel. On Totalisation of Computable Functions in a Distributive Environment International Journal of Parallel, Emergent and Distributed Systems, Volume 37, Number 3, October 2021.

#### **In-Progress**

(added only for the sake of showing progress on PhD applications)

#### • Asymptotically Efficient Maliciously-Secure DORAM and RAM-MPC

We give the first malicious construction of Distributed ORAM while matching the asymptotics of the best-known semi-honest constructions. As a corollary we give the *first* maliciously-secure MPC with logarithmic random access.

B. Falk, D. Noble, R. Ostrovsky, M. Shtepel, J. Zhang

Intend to submit to Crypto23 (early February)

# • Practical Maliciously-Secure DORAM & RAM-MPC

We construct the most practically efficient DORAM to date. We provide an open-source implementation that we contribute to Xiao Wang's EMP-toolkit. For practical database sizes of upwards of 2<sup>23</sup> elements, we beat previous constructions (which achieved only semi-honest security) by a factor of at least 100x.

B. Falk, S. Kelman D. Noble, R. Ostrovsky, M. Shtepel, J. Zhang

Intend to submit to USENIX23 (early February)

### **FUNDING & AWARDS**

• NSF REU funding for summer 2022. Granted for work on secure multiparty computation advised Prof. Rafail Ostrovsky at UCLA.

# ACADEMIC ACTIVITIES

# Advocate for Community College Researchers

Sep 2022 - present

- Create resources to encourage and onboard transfer students into research, including two programs for admitted students in Spring 22.
- Invited to speak on the Engineering Research Presentations & Panel (only transfer student) at UCLA Engineering
- Research-oriented talk Las Positas Community College (expected, January 2023)

# Undergraduate Research Mentor

Oct 2022 - present

Cryptography research at UCLA

• Induct Stephen Kelman to research, with emphasis on teaching cryptographic implementation. Stephen is now a full coauthor on "Practical Maliciously-Secure DORAM & RAM-MPC."

Organizer

Sep 2022 - present

UCLA TCS Guild

• Start and organize the UCLA Theoretical Computer Science Guild, UCLA's (first?) theoretical computer science community. Meet on a weekly basis, discussing topics in theoretical computer science.

# WORK EXPERIENCE

# Cryptographic advisor

Sep 2022 - present

Holonym Foundation

- Advise Holonym Foundation on cryptographic matters, mostly in MPC and ZK, with emphasis on shared-input shared-output psuedorandom functions.
- Largely on pause during Fall 2022 due to paper writing and P.h.D. applications.

STEM Tutor

Sep 2019 - March 2021

Pleasanton, CA

Matan's Tutoring Business

- Tutor middle and high school students primarily in math, but also in biology, programming, and history.
- Over the entire period, had about 6 students, on average meeting with 3 students a week, each for an hour.

Founder, Desginer

June 2019 - May 2020

Pleasanton, CA

RawGNARLY! (fashion brand)

- Founded and operated RAWGNARLY!, a fashion brand all about having fun with your friends.
- Sold about 120 garments, both locally in Pleasanton (about 100) and all across the US (about 20).
- Designed garments, photographed lookbooks, created advertisement, built website, negotiated with vendors (US & abroad).

# RELEVANT COURSE WORK

Graduate cryptography sequence + special topics (winter 23'), graduate communication complexity theory, graduate quantum computing, graduate computational complexity theory (winter 23'), graduate theory hits of 21'st century (winter 23'), real analysis sequence, probability theory sequence, linear algebra sequence, group theory, enumerative combinatorics, required CS curriculum.